当初同我来这的男人
The man I came here with
是一个可靠而有志气的外交官
was a dependable, ambitious diplomat.
你是怎么了?
What's happening to you?
必须找人取代该亚法
Caiaphas who must be replaced.
要是没手腕 就别搞政治游戏
Don't play politics unless you're good at it.
即使面前是刀山火海 我们仍要无畏前行
We must push away our fear as we recognize the persecution we face.
我是扫罗
I'm Saul.
我来扫除这些渎神者
I have come to remove these blasphemers.
用尽一切办法
Do whatever is necessary.
尽量拿上行李!
Take what you can!
我才不会被这个男人和他的威胁所吓倒
I will not be cowed by this man and his threats.
这是我的土地 我要留下来
This was my land. I'm staying.
- 还有我  - 我们耶路撒冷见
- And me.  - See you in Jerusalem.
那里! 抓住他!
There! Take him!
不!
No!
我要毁了你!
I will crush you!
放马过来!
You will try!
本片涉及圣经内容的名词 段落 均参照和合本翻译
公元: 圣经续 第一季第7集
--==圣城家园SCG字幕组 http://hdscg.com/==--
耶路撒冷
仅供翻译交流使用, 禁止用于商业用途
协调: 影子
翻译: 飘飘行天下 波特妹子
翻译: 小黄不小黄 奥利奥
校对: 飘飘行天下 影子
扫罗!
Saul!
那个拿撒勒人的信众就躲在这片区域
The Nazarene followers are hiding in this area.
他们在哪?
Where are they?
耶稣告诉我们...
Jesus told us...
这酒...
that this wine...
是他的血...
was his blood...
而这饼...
and this bread...
是他的身体
his body.
妈妈! 妈妈!
Mom! Mom!
我们现今吃下喝下它们 好叫我们有力气
We eat and drink them now to give us the strength
为他见证
to bear witness to him
与他同在
and to live in unity with him.
圣灵叫我必须去撒玛利亚
The Holy Spirit tells me I must go to Samaria.
要让他的道传遍各地
The word needs to be heard everywhere.
我不觉得到撒玛利亚会有何益处 腓力
I don't think it'll be any better in Samaria, Philip.
要是他们发现你来自耶路撒冷...
If they discover you're from Jerusalem...
他们会叫你粉身碎骨
they'll tear you apart.
肯定有善良的撒玛利亚人
I'm sure there are some good Samaritans.
我会找到他们的
I'll find them.
大家分散开
Break it down.
彻底搜查
Search everywhere.
保持安静 小心点
Keep quiet. Be careful.
我们走吧
Let's go.
你们忠于神和神殿
Your loyalty is to God and the temple,
而非基督
not your Jesus.
把他们带走
Take them away.
快走!
Move!
你与五个人讲道
For every five people you talk to,
他们又会分别再传与五个人
they'll talk to five more.
要不了多久我们就会多如繁星
Soon we'll be as numerous as the stars.
玛利亚
Mary.
他们的父母被扫罗逮起来
Their parents were arrested by Saul.
我们会保他们平安
We'll keep them safe.
扫罗封锁了街道
You should think about leaving, too,
你也该考虑离开这
while Saul is off the streets.
他找的是你
It's you he's after.
民众一直投奔我们而来
People are coming to us all the time.
要是我们不提供庇护 他们可怎么办?
What would they do if we weren't here to give shelter?
我该走了
I should go while I can.
大家保重
Take care, all of you.
大帝在来的路上
The Emperor is coming.
到耶路撒冷来?
To Jerusalem?
也没人预先告诉我
I've had no warning, either.
他马上就要到了
His arrival is imminent.
他为何而来?
Why is he coming?
我不知道
I don't know.
但要是他在我们身上挑出错
But if he finds fault in either of us,
肯定会施加惩罚
he will take action.
他可无权对神殿指手画脚
He has no power over the temple.
该亚法 他是皇帝
Caiaphas, he's the Emperor.
要是他打算剥掉我们俩的官服 他就能做到
If he decides to strip us both of our positions, he will.
要是他决定把你关在神殿里
If he decides to burn the temple to the ground
烧成白地 他就能做到
with you inside it, he will.
我们是一荣俱荣 一损俱损
We stand or fall together on this.
我期望得到你的全面支持
I expect your full support.
街上的冲突必须要终止了
The violence on the streets has to cease.
把拿撒勒人的信徒聚集起来是犹太人的事
Rounding up the followers of the Nazarene is a Jewish matter.
亲爱的女士 在大帝造访期间
For the duration of the Emperor's visit, dear lady,
则是罗马人的事
is very much a Roman one.
你还希望我们为他的来访提供资金援助?
You also expect us to help pay for his visit?
没错
I do.
只要不是为了神做事
I can't use temple funds
我就不能使用神殿的资金
for anything other than God's work.
你可是大祭司啊!
You're the high priest!
我可以减少逮捕行动
The arrests I can curtail.
至于这个资金问题 不能由神殿解决
As for these extra funds, they can't come from the temple.
不过倒是有私人可以提供援助
But they could come from a private source.
我会派哥尼流去取钱
I'll send Cornelius to collect.
我们居然要在提庇留身上慷慨解囊?
We're to lavish money on Tiberius,
他可是一声令下就让成千上万
the man who expelled thousands of our people
我们的人民流离失所的人
from their homes in Rome on a whim?
为了取悦罗马人 你究竟要走到哪步田地?
How far will you go to keep Rome happy?
我们可没那些钱
We don't have the money.
我们当然没有
We don't, no.
撒玛利亚
我帮你
Let me help you.
我还以为你禁止我进入这座房子
As I understood it, you'd banned me from this house.
没错
I had.
但和你女儿讨论之后
But in discussion with your daughter,
我只好与你和解
I felt compelled to offer the hand of reconciliation.
这对彼此都好
This is for the good of us all.
我可以原谅你妄图取代我的愚蠢行径
Your clumsy attempt to unseat me can be forgiven.
六万银币? 你疯了吗?
60,000 denarii? Are you insane?
我会破产的
I'll be bankrupt.
这钱是送给彼拉多 还是更糟 给提庇留?
Is this money bound for Pilate or, worse, Tiberius?
我想送给谁就送给谁
It's bound for wherever I choose to send it.
我明白你和罗马关系匪浅
I know you have a special relationship with Rome,
但别以为每个人都感到高兴
but don't presume that everyone is happy about it.
高兴是有代价的 亚那
Happiness comes at a price, Annas.
这就是你的代价
This is yours.
大帝一来
With the Emperor coming,
内务处就在招人了
households are taking on more staff.
你说我们留在耶路撒冷太危险了
You told me it was too dangerous for us to stay in Jerusalem,
而你现在又想替罗马人工作?
and now you want to work for the Romans?
城里大部分食物都被拿去供给他们了
Most of the city's food's been taken in to feed them.
要是我进了内务处
If I'm part of a household,
我就有机会去厨房
I'll have access to the kitchens.
真高兴你是我们的人
I'm glad you're on our side.
嗯?
Hmm?
我能帮你什么 朋友?
Can I help you, friend?
终于有个仁慈的人了
A kind face at last.
我叫伊扎克
My name is Yitzhak.
腓力
Philip.
你从哪来 腓力?
Where have you come from, Philip?
耶路撒冷
Jerusalem.
大多数耶路撒冷来的人
Most people who come from Jerusalem
都避开撒玛利亚的城市... 太危险了
avoid Samaritan cities... too dangerous.
他们拿走了你的鞋
They took your shoes.
还有个坠子
And a pendant.
是我母亲的 对我意义重大
Belonged to my mother. Meant a lot to me.
到市集去吧
Come to the marketplace.
奇迹即将上演
Wonders are about to be performed.
你们在此将目睹一个人的大能...
You're here to witness the great powers of one man...
让人惊叹 治愈一切疾病的能力
The power to amaze, the power to cure all ills,
神的大能!
the power of God himself!
西门...
Simon...
魔法师!
the sorcerer!
告诉我彼得在哪...
Tell me where Peter is...
我们就停手
a nd we'll stop.
再打
Again.
有何贵干?
What do you want?
那是什么?
What is that?
彼拉多下令停止逮捕
Pilate demands that the arrests stop.
该亚法同意了
Caiaphas agrees.
但我是在做神的工
But I'm doing God's work.
在耶路撒冷不行 不能做...
Not in Jerusalem, you're not...
至少大帝在此期间不行
At least not while the Emperor's here.
有过侍候经验的 举手
Those with serving experience, raise your hands.
你 过来
You. Here.
这是什么意思?
What does this mean?
你以后就在巡抚家当差了
Means you're working in the Governor's household.
- 不行 我... 我不能  - 嗯?
- N...no. I... I can't.  - Hmm?
让你在哪做你就得听话
You will work where you're told.
还有谁?
Who else?
腓利... 来自耶路撒冷
Philip... from Jerusalem.
腓利在这儿吗?
Is Philip here?
你需要我的帮助
You're in need of my help.
我的天赋是为大家服务的 让他过来
Know my gift is for all. Let him pass.
你身陷不幸
You have fallen into misfortune,
并且你失去了某样有重大...
and you have lost something of great...
个人意义的东西 对吗?
personal value, yes?
一件坠饰
A pendant,
是已逝的母亲给我的
given to me by my late mother.
我帮你找回来了
It's no longer lost.
你花多少钱买来的?
How much did you pay for this?
还是根本就是你手下的强盗?
Or do the robbers work for you?
看到了吗?
You see?
不是所有人都对我的天赋心存感激
Not everyone is grateful for the gifts that I bring.
你没有天赋
You have no gift,
没有神的大能
no power from God,
只不过是雕虫小技
just cheap trickery.
滚回犹太吧!
Go home to Judea!
加利利
等等我!
Wait for me!
收成好吗?
Good catch?
嘿! 你不能就这么走进来!
Hey! You can't just walk in here!
这是我家!
This is my home!
如果你在找我父亲 他不在家
If you're looking for my father, he's not here.
你是谁?
Who are you?
能不能麻烦你给我点
I don't suppose I could trouble you
水喝... 拜托了
for some water... Please.
如果彼得在耶路撒冷 我会找到他的
If Peter is in Jerusalem, I will find him.
他留在那也好 回来也罢 都没有区别
If he stays there or comes here, doesn't make a difference.
他知道我是谁
He knows who I am.
他知道我的厉害
He knows what I'm capable of.
我的名字是扫罗
My name is Saul.
耶! 大帝驾到!
Yah! The Emperor!
为大帝欢呼! 为大帝欢呼!
Cheer for the Emperor! Cheer for your Emperor!
欢迎提庇留!
You're welcome Tiberius!
喜讯! 喜讯!
Good tidings! Good tidings!
- 为大帝欢呼  - 够了 快走
- Cheer for your Emperor.  - That's it. Come on.
不要杞人忧天了...
Stop expecting the worst...
保持微笑
and smile.
提庇留大帝
Emperor Tiberius.
欢迎您大驾光临
We are honored by your visit.
我要洗澡
I need a bath.
我的妻子克劳迪娅会照顾您
My wife, Claudia, will take care of you
在此期间的起居饮食
for the duration of your stay.
洗澡
A bath.
我叔叔长途跋涉后就是这样
My uncle's always like this after a long journey.
上次在坎帕尼亚 他一连三天没说话
In Campania, he didn't speak for three days.
是不是 卡里古拉?
Isn't that right, Caligula?
别这么叫我 阿格里帕
Don't call me that, Agrippa.
我全名是盖乌斯·尤利乌斯·凯撒·奥古斯都·日耳曼尼库斯
It's Gaius Julius Caesar Augustus Germanicus.
你父亲是位了不起的罗马人
Your father was a great Roman.
欢迎来到耶路撒冷
Welcome to Jerusalem.
你要是知道我们为何来此
You may not be so keen to welcome us
可能就不会这么热烈欢迎我们了
when you find out why we're here.
扫罗说他会找到你的
Saul said he would find you.
他伤害你了吗?
Did he hurt you?
没有
No.
但他威胁你了?
But he threatened you?
他吓到我了
He scared me.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
非常抱歉
I am so sorry.
你不该来的
You shouldn't have come.
耶路撒冷太危险了
Jerusalem is too dangerous.
但我必须要警告你
But I had to warn you.
我们得采取行动
We have to do something.
我知道
I know.
我们今晚安排了一场盛宴
We have arranged a banquet for tonight.
不要宴请
No banquets.
但您得吃东西啊
But you have to eat.
不要宴请 不要公告
No banquets, no proclamations,
没有演说 不收礼物
no addresses, and no gifts.
那就家常便饭吧
A simple meal, then.
如果您想离席
And when you wish to leave,
我会带您回房去
I will show you back to your rooms.
我来送您回屋
I'll see the Emperor to his rooms.
您在此期间
Is there anything in particular you wish to see
有什么特意想看的吗?
while you are here?
只想见你和其他
Just you and anyone else
名义上管理此处的人
who claims to be running this province.
如果大帝是来罢免你的
If the Emperor has come to remove you,
那我们得跟他的继位者
we must avoid dishonor
搞好关系免遭羞辱
by cultivating goodwill with his successor.
你是指卡里古拉?
You mean Caligula?
还有他的朋友
And we must indulge his friend, too,
即便他是希罗底的兄弟 我们也得迁就下他
even if he is the brother of Herodias.
我有神的大能 我可以治愈你母亲
I have the power of God. I can cure your mother.
附着她的鬼很强大
Her demons are strong.
把她关在我触不到的地方
They keep her far from my reach.
把她搬回我的帐篷里
Have her carried back to my tent.
慢着!
Wait!
让我试试
Let me try.
不 不 不
No, no, no, no, no, no.
让他过来
Let him pass.
他觉得自己比我厉害
He thinks he can do what I can't.
如果你失败了
If you fail,
他们会杀了你
they'll kill you.
奉神的儿子
In the name of Jesus,
耶稣之名...
the son of God...
我将你从监牢中释放
I release you from your prison.
这才是真正的奇迹!
It's a true miracle!
这才是真正的能力 耶稣的能力
There is the true power, the power of Jesus.
哦! 哦!
Oh! Oh!
不如罗马婊子们结实...
Not as solid as the Roman whores...
不过够嫩... 足够让未来的皇帝满足一下了
But still... enough flesh to satisfy a future Emperor.
我 呃
I, um
我想你还满意你的房间吧
I take it you are happy with your rooms.
还过得去
They're passable.
我刚刚还在跟这些人说
I was just telling these pups
上次那群犹太人在罗马冒犯你的事情
about the last time the Jews crossed you in Rome.
那些没被我们驱逐或者杀死的人
Those we didn't expel or put to the sword,
都被征用并流放
we conscripted and sent
到了帝国的边疆
to the furthest limits of the empire.
你该这样和他们打交道...
That's how you deal with these people...
用铁腕
with a firm hand.
你有铁腕吗?
Do you have a firm hand?
你还有野心吗 彼拉多?
Do you still harbor ambitions, Pilate?
给我看个没有野心的罗马人
Show me an unambitious Roman,
我就杀给你看看
and I'll show you a dead one.
但是你拼了命才能控制住犹太这样的小省
And yet you struggle to control a minor province like Judea.
这里有特殊情况 凯撒...
There are unique problems here, Caesar...
要和犹太公会 神殿和祭司打交道...
Managing the Sanhedrin, the temple, the priests...
祭司?
Priests?
在叙利亚 那里的巡抚还得对付
In Syria, the Governor has invading Parthians
来犯的安息人
to contend with.
无意冒犯 任何人都会用武力
With all due respect, anyone can wield a sword.
管理犹太需要外交手段和策略
Judea requires diplomacy and tact.
我相信我的丈夫非常具备这些能力
These are qualities I believe my husband has in abundance,
而这些能力让他受到尊重和敬重
qualities that have led to a respect and esteem
这倒是少有
seldom seen in these situations.
我奉圣父 圣子和圣灵的名
I baptize you in the name of the father
为你施洗
and of the son and of the Holy Spirit.
你是否悔改你的罪?
Do you repent your sins?
我悔改
I do.
我奉...
I baptize you...
圣父 圣子耶稣和圣灵的名
in the name of the father and of the son, Jesus Christ,
为你施洗
and of the Holy Spirit.
谢谢你
Thank you.
这已经不是第一次
It's not the first time
在耶路撒冷出现骚乱了
there's been unrest in Jerusalem.
这地方到底怎么了?
What is it about this place?
各地的人都被吸引到这里来...
People are drawn here from all over...
各有不同的信仰和信念
people of many faiths and beliefs.
这就是你感受到的那股能量
That's the energy you feel.
是让我好奇的能量
It's what made me curious.
你喜欢这里吗?
You like it here?
这城市最好的地方在于...
The best thing about this city...
它离我们在海边的家只有一天的路程
is that it's one day's journey to our home on the coast.
您在这里很安全
You are safe here.
我是大帝
I'm the Emperor.
我在哪里都不安全
I'm not safe anywhere.
你也许能吓倒小孩子
You might stoop to scaring children,
但是你的迫害只能让我们心中圣灵之火
but your persecution only makes the Holy Spirit
烧得更旺
burn stronger within us.
那就更该结束你的生命了
All the more reason to put an end to you.
你终结不了我们的 扫罗
You can't put an end to me, Saul.
我在这里是神的旨意
It's God's will I'm here,
而我何时何地死也凭神的旨意
and it'll be God's will where and when I am to die.
也许我在此也是神的旨意 对吧?
Perhaps it is God's will that I am here, too, yes?
我们一定马上就能知道
I'm sure we'll find out
我们之间
who is to live and who is to die
谁死谁活!
soon enough!
呵
Huh.
什么? 等等!
What? Wait!
你就只和他动动嘴吗?
You're just going to talk to him?!
彼得!
Peter!
足够了
It's enough.
不! 不!
No! No!
我们不是暴力的人
We are not men of violence.
但是 彼得 我们终于抓到他了
But, Peter, we've finally got him.
如果神真是在指引你们的话
You'd have thought that God
你们本以为他
could have given you all a clearer vision
能让你们预见的更清晰吧
if, in fact, he was guiding you.
很高兴知道你还在耶路撒冷 彼得
Good to know you're still in Jerusalem, Peter.
你感觉到任何变化吗?
Do you feel any different?
把你的刀给我
Give me your knife.
没事的
It's all right.
我已经受洗了 我已经受洗了
I've been baptized. I've been baptized.
我可以治愈它的
I'll heal it.
为什么? 为什么我没有得到腓利那样的能力 嗯?
Why? Why have I not been given the same power as Philip, eh?
我可以给手绑上绷带了吗?
Can I bandage my hand now?
我相信犯人的早饭一定很棒
I trust the condemned man ate a hearty breakfast.
你们昨晚休息的好吗?
Did you rest well last night?
很好
Oh, yes.
我们休息得很好
We did.
希律·安提帕和希罗底
Herod Antipas and Herodias.
你们来干什么?
What are you doing here?
大帝召见我
The Emperor summoned me.
我们以为你去耶路撒冷的时候
We thought you would have paid us a visit
会顺路拜访一下我们 弟弟
on your way to jerusem, brother.
他坚持要去 但是我强迫他跟着大部队走
He insisted, but I forced him to stay with the caravan.
希律 欢迎来到犹太
Herod. Welcome to Judea.
我就知道我认识你
I thought I recognized you.
你是那个拿撒勒人的信徒
You're a follower of the Nazarene.
你在这里干什么?
What are you doing here?
呃... 我需要工作
Uh... I needed a job.
好帮你的朋友?
To help your friends?
他们也在这里吗?
Are they here, too?
所有人都走了
Everyone's gone.
我自己一个人
I'm on my own.
告诉我有什么理由不此时此刻
You tell me why I shouldn't have you arrested
就把你逮捕了
right here, right now.
悉听尊便
Do what you have to do.
你不害怕吗?
You're not scared?
有人教导我要爱我的敌人
I've been taught to love my enemies,
祝福那些诅咒我的人
to bless those who curse me.
不要再让我看到你靠近巡抚
Don't let me see you near the Governor again.
懂了吗?
Understood?
我相信眼下的情况没人能比我
I believe I have handled the situation here
处理得更好了
as well as anyone could.
这场暴动中有多少罗马人被杀了?
How many romans have been killed in this insurrection?
只有一个
Just one.
凶手已经被抓到并处决了
And his killer has been caught and executed.
有多少狂热分子被清除了呢? 很多
How many zealots have been eliminated? Many.
倒不如说是到处乱抓人
Some might say people were rounded up indiscriminately.
安提帕 我以为你把耶稣这事的责任
I thought you'd have been happy, Antipas,
推到我头上会很开心
having given over responsibility for Jesus to me.
那个叛乱者耶稣  大祭司宣称他
Jesus, the rebel, whom the high priest claimed
给神殿带来了很大的麻烦 他已经被钉死了...
was stirring up trouble for the temple has been crucified...
他的追随者们都逃散了
And his followers scattered.
一个很小的狂热教派
A small fanatic faction.
多亏了我 已经不复存在了
A faction no longer, thanks to me.
如果你统治这里你会怎么做?
What would you have done had you been ruling?
哦 我会早下决定的
Oh, I'd have been more decisive sooner.
我对巡抚无意冒犯
No offense to the Governor,
但是我会把这场骚乱扼杀在摇篮里
but I would have killed this movement at its birth
并用罗马的强大军力
and used the military might of Rome
歼灭任何叛乱之象
to annihilate any signs of rebellion.
将逆贼粉身碎骨
Smashed their bones and crushed their skulls.
我能传唤一个人吗?
Can I call someone to speak?
叫吧
Go ahead.
提庇留大帝
Emperor Tiberius.
你传犹太人为你辩护?
You call a Jew to plead for you?
虽然我看似来为巡抚辩护
It may appear as if I'm here to plead for the Governor,
实则我们共同保卫人民
but we united to protect the people
和这座城市不受邪念侵染
and the city from a contagion.
历年来 我相信彼拉多和我
Over the years, I believe Pilate and I
逐渐达成共识
have come to an understanding
明确了治理现状的最佳方式
on how best to deal with these situations.
你是指 在乱贼对你的地位构成威胁时
You mean he executes rebels for you
他替你将他们铲除干净?
when they're a threat to your status?
耶稣是众人的公害
Jesus was a danger to us all.
他用妄语和亵渎之言煽动群众
He stirred the people with lies and blasphemy.
他想破除包括你在内的
He wanted to tear down all institutions,
一切制度 一切权威
all authority, including yours.
必须有人制止他 他也确实被制止了
He had to be stopped, and was.
而你也一心想保护你的至圣所
You also had to preserve your holy of holies.
至圣所: 犹太圣殿最内层的位置 被认为是耶和华的住所
不是吗?
Am I right?
伟大的将领庞贝不是去过那内殿
Didn't the great General Pompey find his way
然后说里面空空如也吗?
into that chamber and say there was nothing there?
我们无需雕像或画像来证明其存在 因为他必在那里
We need no idols or images because we know he's there.
谁?
Who?
神
God.
我还从没见过犹太人的神
I've never met a Jewish God.
或许改天我去拜访下他
Maybe I could pay him a visit.
憋着你的蠢话
Keep your idiotic thoughts to yourself.
凯撒 任何新上任的官员都要花数年时间
It would take years, Caesar, for any new administration
才能有我和大祭司
to reach the level of understanding
对此事的认知
the high priest and I have.
如果你需要...
If you need more...
可以退下了
You may leave.
凯撒 如果能透露一下您的意向
Caesar, it would be helpful to know
那便再好不过了
in which direction you intend to turn next.
我会告知你的
You'll be told.
凯撒
Caesar.
停手吧!
Stop!
他不是彼得!
It's not Peter!
你在提庇留面前
You stood in front of Tiberius
为彼拉多求情?!
and pleaded Pilate's cause?!
我必须这么做
I had to.
那万一功亏一篑
And what if, despite everything,
大帝执意要将彼拉多撤职呢?
the Emperor decides to replace Pilate?
- 到时我们会落得什么下场?!  - 我不知道
- Where will that leave us?!  - I don't know.
我和家人撕破脸 可不是为了一句
I haven't risked my relationship with my family
"我不知道"
for "I don't know."
你必须要确保事情如我们所愿!
You need to be certain this will fall our way!
我们很快就能知道了 不是吗?
Well, we'll soon find out, won't we?
何事?
What?
遇上麻烦了
We have a problem.
解决掉
Solve it.
解决掉!
Solve it!
是扫罗
It's Saul.
他又开始逮捕民众了
He's back arresting people.
带他们去牢房 亚设
Take them to the cell, Asher.
哇哦! 哇哦
Whoa! Whoa.
停下
Stop.
这是怎么回事?
What's going on here?
我们在逮捕异教徒
We're arresting heretics.
耶稣的信徒
Followers of Jesus.
带去牢房!
To prison!
去牢房!
你干嘛?
What are you doing?
我是罗马人 你胆敢碰我?
I am a Roman. You dare to touch me?
你对这地方的评价很对
You're right about this place.
这里的确蕴藏一股能量
It does have a kind of energy.
还有一种精神
and a spirit, too.
能潜入你心底 在某方面改变你
It gets inside, changes you in some way.
在海滨路上...
I saw four vultures...
我看见四只秃鹰
on the Coast Road,
翱翔于空中
riding the air.
我的占卜师告诉我无需担心
My augur tells me not to worry.
秃鹰也可能是吉兆
Vultures can be good omens.
然而来这途中
And yet on the journey here,
我梦见有人出殡
I dreamt of a funeral procession.
这地方让你见到幻象
This place gives you visions.
我有些梦已然成真...
Some of my dreams have come true...
包括梦见拿撒勒人耶稣的事
including one about the Nazarene, Jesus.
但我没梦到会有人在今晚丧命
But I haven't dreamt about anyone dying tonight.
晚安 大帝
Good night, Emperor.
最后的机会了... 趁现在没动静
Last chance... come with us
跟我们走吧
while it's quiet.
你知道我们不能走
You know we can't.
但我们可以重获自由...
But we would be free...
自由布道 洗礼
free to preach and baptize again.
我若跟你们走 扫罗又会追去
If I go with you, I'll just drag Saul after you.
再说了 这里还有很多事未办完
And, anyway, there's much to do here.
我们必须有人留在耶路撒冷
Some of us have to stay in Jerusalem.
照顾这位
Look after this one.
我觉得应该是她照顾我
I think she'll be the one looking after me.
再见 兄弟 多多保重
Goodbye, brother. Take care.
你也是 神与你同在
You, too. God be with you.
但万一提庇留觉得没了大祭司的协助
But what if it seems to Tiberius that I'm incapable of ruling
我无法管好这地方呢?
without the help of my high priest?
更何况有安提帕在伺机觊利...
And with Antipas waiting to take advantage...
安提帕是个自私的阴险小人
Antipas is a self-serving viper.
但还需要他来维持秩序
But he is necessary for maintaining order.
他没有意识到的是
What he fails to realize
若我们其中一人倒下...
is that if one of us falters...
提庇留可能会让我们全部分崩离析
Tiberius could tear us all down.
他不过是个年迈的老人
He's a tired old man
开始觉得自己命不久矣
who's starting to feel the shadows closing in.
但他还是有权将我逐出犹太
But he is still capable of expelling me from Judea.
然后会怎么样呢?
And what happens then?
我们回不了罗马 会被众人耻笑
We can't go back to Rome. We'll be a laughingstock.
你在这可是政绩斐然
Your record here is exemplary.
我觉得提庇留已经意识到了
I think Tiberius is starting to see for himself
耶路撒冷的问题很特殊
the unique problems that Jerusalem presents.
我们只需保持冷静
We just have to hold our nerve.
扫罗
Saul.
你跟我来
I need you to follow me.
有件事你最好知道
There's something you should hear.
告诉这些人你刚说的拿撒勒人彼得的消息
Tell these men what you told us about the Nazarene, Peter.
你这个家伙 说话 否则我再打烂你的皮
Speak up, man, or I'll flay you again.
彼得离开了
Peter's gone.
去那里?
Where?
他... 他往北去了
H... he headed north.
那里?
Where?
大马士革 大马士革
Damascus, Damascus.
放他下来
Get him down.
这是奖励你的
You've earned that.
他上当了
He took the bait.
告诉一个人他最渴望听到的话 不上当才怪
Tell a man what he's dying to hear, and they always will.
你越来越像个政治家了
You're becoming quite the politician.
信仰最大的敌人是否...
Will the biggest enemy of the faith...
- 你是谁?  - 我是耶稣
- Who are you?  - I am Jesus.
会面临审判之日?
Face judgement day?